# 搞深点的
Deeper
# 掐深点的啊
Pick deeper?
# 我这边挨着挨着掐的
I'm picking one next to another
# 今天我们摘一点这个空心菜回去吃
Today, we're picking some water spinach to eat
# 我四伯爷种这个长得太快了 吃不完
Uncle planted it. It grows too fast, we can't finish it
# 搞不赢吃这个
We can't win against it
# 你哪里搞得赢哦
How can you win against it?
# 还有这些辣椒再不摘的话晒都给它晒烂了
And these peppers. If we don't pick them now, they'll rot under the sun
# 然后待会再上去摘点梨吃一下
Then we'll climb up there and pick some pears to eat
# 现在梨也熟了
Now the pears are also ripe
# 多摘点
I'll pick more
# 煎得到两顿都可以了
It'll be good
# 这个菜啊都是自己种的
We planted these veggies ourselves
# 要吃的话现摘
We pick whenever we want
# 而且就在我们家院子
And they are just in our yard
# 随时都可以整来吃
Pick whenever we want
# 就是
Exactly
# 根子弄来扔了就是
Just get rid of the roots
# 可以吃两顿了这个
This is enough for two meals
# 好
Alright
# 还有一些没掐到
I haven't picked them all
# 摘点海椒嘛 加点海椒炒起安逸
Let's pick some peppers to cook together. It will be nice
# 要的啊
Sure
# 嗯
Hmm
# 这个我感觉没得好辣的这个海椒
I feel like these peppers are not really spicy
# 这个是二荆条
These are Erjingtiao
# 啊
Ah
# 再弄几个朝天椒一起炒
Also some Chaotianjiao to cook together
# 要的啊
Sure
# 这种就辣哦
These are the spicy ones
# 啊 混在里面
Ah, put them together
# 我还弄断了一个枝
I broke a branch
# 还长开花了你看
It even bloomed. Look
# 嗯嗯
Hmm
# 好
Alright
# 摘点鱼香嘛 下次可以煮点鱼
How about some Yuxiang? We can make a fish stew next time
# 可以安
Of course
# 这不摘死都死了（过季）
If we don't pick, it's going to die (out of season)
# 等我下次去钓点鱼回来烧给你吃
Next time I go fishing, I'll cook it for you
# 要的啊
Sure
# 他们都在打谷子了嘎
They have been harvesting rice already?
# 是哦 我们都要迟点
Yeah. We are a bit late
# 人家那些 我今天出去看到那些
The other people-- I mean those I saw today
# 基本上都要打完了
They have basically finished harvesting
# 是 我上去弄点梨子下来吃
Yeah. I'll climb up and pick some pears
# 四伯爷帮我扶着楼梯
Could you hold the ladder for me, uncle?
# 拿个篮子上来嘛不是
Do you need a basket?
# 口袋
Bag
# 要的嘛 拿个口袋上来
Sure. Get a bag!
# 四伯爷你的背后有个笋子虫 那儿
Uncle, there's a bamboo weevil behind you. Over there
# 哪里哦
Where?
# 那儿那儿
Over there
# 笋子虫
Bamboo weaver
# 这么大的梨 太可惜了
What a big pear! But it's wasted
# 真的是
Geez
# 这个也烂了
This is rotten, too
# 哇 这个巨无霸这个
Wow, this one is gigantic
# 这个也有一斤
This is over 1 jin (500g)
# 这个好
A good one
# 先暂时放在一起
Put them together for now
# 这个呢
How about this?
# 这个也摘了吧
I'm also picking it
# 看这个梨
Let's check this pear
# 哇 这个也挺好
Wow, this is also good
# 二娃 你在那儿站起看那边的三个
# 译者注：这里的“二娃”应该指的是王刚而不是漆二娃。为了避免读者混乱就模糊处理了
Kid, stand up and look over there! There are three
# 那边那三个
Three over there
# 我过去看
I'll take a look
# 这个都烂了
This is already rotten
# 那外面的三个干脆一哈摘了
How about picking those three together?
# 免得它坏了可惜了
Before they rot and get wasted
# 好我过去看 大丰收了今年
OK, I'll go and check! What a harvest this year!
# 哇 这个最大
Wow, this is the biggest one
# 四伯爷这个起码一斤多
Uncle, this is at least 1 jin, or even more
# 真的安逸今年子这个
It's really nice this year
# 好大哦那个
That's a very big one
# 哇塞 这个呢
Wow, how about this one?
# 这个也是好的
Also a good one
# 最近这个天确实很热
It's really hot recently
# 摘个梨满头大汗
I just picked some pears, and I'm already soaked in sweat
# 现在准备下去了
Now I'm getting down
# 今天收获了几十斤梨
Today, we harvested dozens of jin of pears
# 好 现在我要下去了
Alright, now I'm getting down
# 四伯爷过来提哈梨子 多得很
Uncle, come here and take some pears. There's a lot
# 来嘛 四伯爷
Come, uncle
# 重得很
It's heavy
# 几十斤这个
Dozens of jin
# 丢都丢了好多个
You already threw away many pears
# 丢都丢了十几个
Threw away a dozen of pears
# 我们家的梨这么大一个
Our pears are like this big
# 害怕往年都没有结到这么大个
I guess they wern't this large in the past years?
# 都这么大个
They've all been this big
# 可能都是被鸟吃了
Maybe the birds ate them
# 被鸟吃了 蜜蜂也要蛰
Birds ate them. And bees stung them
# 蜜蜂要蛰
Even bees?
# 蜜蜂爱得很 这些烂的就是蜜蜂干的事
Bees love them! They made those rotten ones
# 好梨子它就要吃安
These are good pears. They also want to eat some
# 我们去年的时候正好在修房子
Last year we were building the house
# 那个时候梨全部被鸟吃了
The pears were all eaten by the birds
# 所以今年我们就把它给（裹起来)
So this year, we've wrapped them up
# 不关事 这个皮子有点厚我就把它削厚点
The peel is a bit thick, so I'll cut deeper
# 我少吃点 我整不动
I'll just have a little. I can't bite
# 我还是少划点
I'll have a
# 看嘛 这才是本地梨子的味道
Check it out, this is how local pears taste like
# 慢点哈
Enjoy
# 好吃嘛
Is it good?
# 嗯
Hmm
# 水分特别足
This is especially juicy
# 这梨子树好多年了
This pear tree is so many years old
# 水分足得很这梨子的
This pear is very juicy
# 自带一点点果酸味有一点点酸
It has a bit of fruit acidity
# 我们这棵树好久了
How old is the tree?
# 几十年了
Dozens of years
# 好多安
How many?
# 我记事的时候就有了
Since I was a kid
# 应该这个树有50年左右吧
The tree should be about fifty years old
# 然后下面把它保护好一点
# 译者注：这里中文字幕似乎有误，我听到的是“下一年把它保护好一点”
And we are going to protect it better next year
# 结出更多的梨 到时候跟粉丝分享
So that it yields more pears. I'll share with you then
# （以前）那会结得才安逸 过路的都要摘
Before, it was bearing even more. Even passersby could pick some
# 你问你伯爷嘛
Your uncle knows it
# 你伯爷背上是啥子安
What's on the back of your uncle?
# 石灰
Lime
# 摘个梨我全身都湿透了
I'm soaked in sweat after picking these pears
# 好 本期视频就到这里 拜拜
Alright, that's it for this video. Bye bye!
# 等会我吃这个
I'll have this one later
# 拿回去撒
Take it home
# 带回去嘛把这些
Take them back home